Guide to the Ezra Pound Miscellany
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Ezra Pound miscellany
1909-1973
YCAL MSS 182
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.09
(5 boxes)
The collection consists of letters and a few manuscripts by or related to Ezra Pound. Correspondents include Ubaldo degli Uberti; Ethel de Courcy Duncan; Robert Duncan; Gladys Hines; Lewis Maverick; Donald J. Paquette; Odon Por; and Louis Zukofsky. Manuscripts include holographs of "To Our Lady of Vicarious Atonement" and "What I Feel about Walt Whitman" by Pound and biographical notes on Pound by Lewis Maverick.
Pound, Ezra, 1885-1972
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired by gift and purchase from various sources between 1935 and 1981. Source information is recorded on each folder. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 5: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Associated Materials
Ezra Pound Papers, YCAL MSS 43.
Ezra Pound Papers Addition, YCAL MSS 53.
Scope and Contents
The Ezra Pound Miscellany consists of single items and small groups of material relating to Ezra Pound that were acquired from various sources by Yale between 1935 and 1981. The Miscellany has been organized into two series: I. Correspondence; and II. Writings.
Series I, Correspondence, is organized into two alphabetically arranged subseries: Ezra Pound Correspondence and Third-Party Correspondence. As Dorothy Pound frequently acted as amanuensis for Pound during his years in St. Elizabeth's, her letters to his correspondents have been interfiled with his in the first subseries and their presence noted in the folder descriptions. Her own personal correspondence with Drew Ponder-Greene, on the other hand, is found in Third-Party Correspondence.
Correspondents represented in Series I include several of Pound's literary friends from the 1920s and 1930s; political journalists and others with whom Pound corresponded on economic theory, Fascism, and the flaws in Western democracies; and scholars and well-wishers who first contacted Pound during his confinement in St. Elizabeth's Hospital after World War II.
Early literary correspondents represented in Series I include John Cournos, Joseph Vogel and Louis Zukofsky. Pound's letters to them largely concern his attempts to "organize" the young writers and to persuade them to found new little magazines and to publish new work, including but not limited to Pound's own. Pound offers advice on publication, generalized commentary on criticism and recent literary history, and suggestions for sources of financial support and patronage. Vogel broke off contact with Pound after 1929, but Cournos and Zukofsky continued to correspond with him throughout the 1930s, as his letters became increasingly preoccupied with Social Credit, economics, and criticisms of Franklin Roosevelt and the New Deal.
Pound's correspondence with Gladys Hynes focuses on their shared musical interests. His letters contain news of concerts by Olga Rudge and George Antheil. In a 1923 letter, he commented that "I am glad you liked the Villon. That makes six or seven people." Letters to Ethel Duncan (folders 19-22) likewise discuss Rudge and her career as a violinist; Pound writes of "buying O. a fiddle " and sends Duncan a laudatory review of one of her 1933 concerts in Rapallo. During and after the Italian invasion of Ethiopia, Pound's letters to Duncan too become mostly political. He repeatedly requests information about Charles Maurras and Action Française; attacks Roosevelt, the British government and the "Rothschild" banking system; and offers qualified praise of Mussolini and the Fascist government.
The most overtly political letters in the Miscellany are those Pound wrote to the Hungarian economist and Fascist Odon Por, whose Italy's Policy of Social Economics 1939-1940 Pound translated into English in 1941, and to Ubaldo degli Uberti, a retired admiral who was to become undersecretary of the Navy in the Salò regime. Pound's letters to Por, in both English and Italian, are located in folders 53-60 and contain his thoughts on autarky; Social Credit; the foreign policies of Mussolini and Hitler; the decadence of England and America; and similar topics. They also contain frequent demands for "American news," information on members of Mussolini's government, and the publication of his own articles on political topics. For example, a letter dated 13-14 April 1940 inquires urgently about air mail to the United States and access to the Japan Times; asks humorously "When did you say France wd/ throw in her hand? I fergit whether you counted on our spending the Fourth of July in Paris" and suggests the burning of the British Embassy on Bastille Day; and concludes "Do you git ANY American news?" The final letter to Por in the Miscellany, dated 29 December 1941, states Pound's determination to continue his broadcasts on Radio Roma, calling the war a war between "due principii...due ordine" and resolving to broadcast "in nome mio, con mio proprio voce: non anonimamente."
Pound's letters to Ubaldo degli Uberti are briefer but similar in tone and subject. A 29 July 1940 letter comments on German film of the first week of the invasion of the Soviet Union and regrets that the Americans did not participate: "they lose out on it/ the danes will have something they haven't." Another frequent topic is Pound's work on a translation of Confucius and his hopes that it will be read carefully by members of the Salò government.
During his confinement in St. Elizabeth's Hospital following the war, Pound continued to write at length on political and economic topics to both old and new correspondents. Those represented in the Miscellany include Father Vianney Devlin, Robert Duncan, Aida Mastrangelo, the Chinese scholar Lewis Maverick, Donald J. Paquette, and Tiffany Thayer. The collection also contains letters written during this period to Margaret Anderson, Osmond Beckwith, Anne and Michael Lebeck, and John J. Slocum.
Pound's exchanges with these correspondents sometimes focused on topics of particular interest to each: Confucian scholarship with Lewis Maverick, Catholic theology and history with the Franciscan Vianney Devlin, the history of the Little Review and literary magazines with Margaret Anderson. In almost all cases, however, Pound continued to advocate his political and economic ideas, despite his realization that " no body has to agree wiff me now. esp. at this address," as he commented to Duncan in a 1947 letter (Box 1, folder 23). He frequently sent them elaborate annotated reading lists, requested that they contact each other and others whom Pound identified as "useful" or "serious," read and critiqued works that his correspondents sent to him, and occasionally commented on his personal history and on the current state of literature.
Pound thanked his correspondents for presents, suggested appropriate future presents, and requested or refused requests for visits at St. Elizabeth's. The logistics of these were almost always conveyed in letters written by Dorothy Pound, who arranged permissions, meeting times, and occasionally transportation and lodging for the invitees.
Several of his correspondents, including Anderson, Maverick, and Paquette, annotated his letters extensively in attempts to clarify Pound's compressed allusions and their own reactions: Anderson commented on one undated letter, "I understood almost nothing in this letter," for example, while Paquette recorded his increasing distaste for Pound's vigorously expressed defenses of Mussolini and Fascism. Lewis Maverick and Homer Somers also created substantial notes on Pound and his works, and these are located in Series II.
The second subseries, Third-Party Correspondence, is alphabetically arranged by author. Dorothy Pound's letters to the book collector Drew Ponder-Greene are located in Box 3, folder 97. Dorothy sends news of Ezra's health, noting that he no longer talks but walks vigorously, describes her life alone in Rapallo, and occasionally comments on recently published articles and books on Pound. Folders 98 and 99 contain Homer Pound's letters to two of his son's publishers, requesting catalogs and copies of his books.
Series II, Writings, is housed in Box 4 and has been organized into two subseries: Writings by Pound and Writings of Others. Writings by Pound is located in folders 102-107 and includes holographs of the early poem "To Our Lady of Vicarious Atonement" and the 1909 prose piece "What I feel about Walt Whitman," as well as typescripts of political prose from the 1930s. In addition to the notes on Pound written by Maverick and Somers, Writings of Others contains a printed copy of D. D. Paige's "Petition" for the release of Pound from St. Elizabeth's Hospital and a reminiscence about Pound by Osmond Beckwith.
Restricted Fragile materials are housed in Box 5.
American literature -- 20th Century; American poetry -- 20th Century; European literature -- 20th Century; Modernism (Literature); Authors; Anderson, Margaret C., 1886-1973; Beckwith, Osmond; Degli Uberti, Riccardo; Degli Uberti, Ubaldo, 1881-1945; Devlin, Vianney M.; Duncan, Ethel de Courcy; Duncan, Robert, 1919-1988; Hynes, Gladys, 1888-1958; Mastrangelo, Aida; Maverick, Lewis A. (Lewis Adams), 1891-; Paquette, Donald J.; Por, Odon; Pound, Dorothy; Pound, Ezra, 1885-1972 -- Knowledge -- China; Pound, Ezra, 1885-1972 -- Political and social views; Pound, Ezra, 1885-1972 -- Views on money; Pound, Ezra, 1885-1972; Thayer, Tiffany, 1902-1959; Zukofsky, Louis, 1904-1978
- Correspondence, 1909-1973; Series I; 1.25; (3 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence, is organized into two subseries, each arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - EZRA POUND CORRESPONDENCE
    - Alden, John, [1947] (Box 1, Folder 1)
      With ALS from Dorothy Pound, 1947 Oct 28
    - Anderson, Margaret, 1950-[53] (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Bagnall, Bernard, 1916 Jun 15 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Beckwith, Osmond, 1948-50 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      With 3 ALS and TLS from Dorothy Pound, 1948-49
    - Cournos, John, 1926-64 (Box 1, Folder 5-7)
    - Davidson, Eugene, [1932] Oct 8 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Devlin, Vianney M., O.F.M, 1953-57 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
    - degli Uberti, Riccardo, 1940-54 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - degli Uberti, Riccardo, 1954-59 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - degli Uberti, Ubaldo, 1934 Apr-Jun (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - degli Uberti, Ubaldo, 1934 Jul-Dec (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - degli Uberti, Ubaldo, 1935-37 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - degli Uberti, Ubaldo, 1938-39 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - degli Uberti, Ubaldo, 1940-41 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - degli Uberti, Ubaldo, 1942-45 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Duncan, Ethel de Courcy, 1932-35 Mar (Box 1, Folder 19-20)
      With "American Violinist Stirs Enthusiasm on Italian Riviera," typescript carbon, 1933
    - Duncan, Ethel de Courcy, 1935 Apr (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Duncan, Ethel de Courcy, 1935-51, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Duncan, Robert, 1947-[50], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 23-24)
      With 9 ALS and telegram from Dorothy Pound, 1946-[50]
      With TLS from Sister Mary Bernetta Quinn to Ezra Pound, 1950 Jul 21
    - Gellert, Lawrence, 1932 Jul 1 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Hynes, Gladys, 1923-35 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Hynes, Gladys, 1948-49 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Hynes, Gladys, 1950-51 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Hynes, Gladys, 1952-54 (Box 1, Folder 29)
      With advertising flyer for the "Square $ Series," printed
    - Hynes, Gladys, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Hynes, Gladys, 1956-58 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Miscellaneous material relating to Gladys Hynes, 1928-58 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Kearns, George, 1950 Dec 18 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Kildare, Owen, n.y. Mar 14 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Lebeck, Anne, 1956-57 (Box 2, Folder 34-35)
      With ANS and notes by Dorothy Pound
    - Lebeck, Morton [later Michael], 1953 Oct 5 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Mastrangelo, Aida, 1950-55 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Mastrangelo, Aida, 1955-59, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Mastrangelo, Aida from Dorothy Pound, 1950-61 (Box 2, Folder 39-40)
    - Maverick, Lewis, 1957 Jul-Aug (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Maverick, Lewis, 1957 Sep (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Maverick, Lewis, 1957-59 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Transcripts of Pound letters by Maverick (Box 2, Folder 44-46)
    - Paquette, Donald J., 1950 Jan-Mar (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Paquette, Donald J., 1950 Apr-May (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Paquette, Donald J., 1950 Jun (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Paquette, Donald J., 1950 Jul-1953 (Box 2, Folder 50)
      With advertisement for The Analects and flyer for Square $ Series, printed
    - Paquette, Donald J. from Dorothy Pound, 1950-51 (Box 2, Folder 51-52)
      With third-party correspondence to Paquette, 1950
    - Por, Odon, 1934 Apr (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Por, Odon, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Por, Odon, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Por, Odon, 1938-39 (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - Por, Odon, 1940 Feb-Jul (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - Por, Odon, 1940 Aug-Nov (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - Por, Odon, 1941 Jan-Apr (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - Por, Odon, 1941, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - Rogers, J. H., 1933 Sep 18 (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - Romm, Charles, 1919 Mar 4 (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - Schwerke, Irving, 1925 Jul 7 (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - Slocum, John J., 1948 Jul-Aug (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - Somers, Homer L., 1945-56 (Box 3, Folder 65)
      With 4 ALS and AN from Dorothy Pound, 1955-56
    - Taylor, Charles
      Related Archival Materials note
      See: Yale University. Provost's Office, Box 1, folder 70
    - Thayer, Tiffany, 1946-56 (Box 3, Folder 66-67)
      With ALS from Dorothy Pound, 1947 Dec, and ALS from Isabel Pound, n.d.
    - Vogel, Joseph, [1927]-29 (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - Wright, Willard Huntington, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - Yale University. Provost's Office, 1966 Apr-May (Box 3, Folder 70)
    - Yale University Press, 1936-38 (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - Zukovsky, Louis, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 72)
      With ALS from Harriet Monroe to EP, 1928 Oct 15
      With typescript carbon, corrected, of "To Fill A Very Real Want," [1928]
    - Zukovsky, Louis, 1929 (Box 3, Folder 73)
    - Zukovsky, Louis, 1930 Jan-Jul (Box 3, Folder 74)
    - Zukovsky, Louis, 1930 Sep-Dec (Box 3, Folder 75-76)
      With layout diagram and typescript of attack by EP on Article 211 of the Postal Code
    - Zukovsky, Louis, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 77-78)
    - Zukovsky, Louis, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 79)
    - Zukovsky, Louis, 1933-40 (Box 3, Folder 80)
      With typescript carbon of "The Functions of Criticism"
      With typescript carbon of "Is America Losing Her Chance?"
      With typescript carbon, signed and annotated, of letter from EP to Philip Hayden of Columbia University, 1940 Feb 6
      With manuscript menu in Italian for a dinner, n.d.
    - Unidentified, 1909 Dec 15 (Box 3, Folder 81)
  - THIRD-PARTY CORRESPONDENCE
    - Agresti, Olivia Rossetti to Gladys Hynes, 1955 May 15 (Box 3, Folder 82)
    - Cookson, William to Lewis Maverick, 1957 Jan-Nov (Box 3, Folder 83)
    - Frampton, Hollis to Lewis Maverick, 1958 Jan-Jul (Box 3, Folder 84)
    - Horton, T. D. [to Lewis Maverick?], 1957 Aug (Box 3, Folder 85)
    - Hynes, Gladys to the Editor of The Observer, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 86)
    - Martell, Charles to Lewis Maverick, 1957-58 (Box 3, Folder 87)
    - Mastrangelo, Aida to Ufficio Culturale dell'ambasciata d'Italia, 1957-58 (Box 3, Folder 88)
    - Maverick, Lewis to Olivia Rossetti Agresti, 1959 Nov 21 (Box 3, Folder 89)
    - Maverick, Lewis to [President Dwight Eisenhower?], 1957 Sep 13 (Box 3, Folder 90)
    - Maverick, Lewis to "Ko", 1957 Sep 9 (Box 3, Folder 91)
    - Maverick, Lewis to Harry Miller, Dec 14 n.y. (Box 3, Folder 92)
    - Maverick, Lewis to Arnando Sapori, 1957 Sep 9 (Box 3, Folder 93)
    - Maverick, Lewis to John Theobald, 1957 Sep-Oct (Box 3, Folder 94)
    - Maverick, Lewis to "Vernon", 1957 Sep 24 (Box 3, Folder 95)
    - Overholser, Winfred to Osmond Beckwith, 1948 May 6 (Box 3, Folder 96)
    - Pound, Dorothy to Drew Ponder-Greene, 1968-73 (Box 3, Folder 97)
      With ALS from Omar Pound, 1973 Dec 8
    - Pound, Homer to The Literary Digest, 1909-1916 (Box 3, Folder 98)
    - Pound, Homer to Yale University Press, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 99)
    - Swabey, Henry to Homer L. Somers, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 100)
    - Zabel, Morton Dauwen to Poetry, 1936 Nov-Dec (Box 3, Folder 101)
- Writings, 1909-1960; Series II; 0.42; (1 box)
  Series II, Writings, is organized into two subseries. The first, Writings by Pound, is arranged alphabetically by title; the second, Writings of Others, is arranged alphabetically by name of author.
  - WRITINGS BY POUND
    - "Definire Parole", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 102)
      Typescript carbon, corrected
    - "Introduction and Vocabulary" (Box 4, Folder 103)
      Typescript carbon, corrected and annotated
    - "Principia Statale" (Box 4, Folder 104)
      Typescript, corrected
    - "The Testament of François Villon", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 105)
      Typescript photostat
    - "To Our Lady of Vicarious Atonement", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 106)
      Holograph
    - "What I feel about Walt Whitman", 1909 (Box 4, Folder 107)
  - WRITINGS OF OTHERS
    - Beckwith, Osmond: "Two Meetings" (Box 4, Folder 108)
      Typescript
    - Maverick, Lewis: Notes on Pound, 1958 Mar, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 109)
    - Maverick, Lewis: Notes on Pound, 1960 Jul, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 110)
    - Maverick, Lewis: Notes on Pound (Box 4, Folder 111)
    - Maverick, Lewis: Notecards, A-F, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 112)
    - Maverick, Lewis: Notecards, G-P, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 113)
    - Maverick, Lewis: Notecards, Q-Z, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 114)
    - Maverick, Lewis: Transcript of a radio program about Pound sent to Lewis Maverick, 1957 Sep 13 (Box 4, Folder 115)
    - Paige, D. D.: "Petition", 1952 (Box 4, Folder 116)
      Printed item With ALS to "Mr. Littlefield," 1952 Oct 10
    - Somers, Homer L.: Notes on Pound, 1945-48, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 117)
- Restricted Fragile, 0.42; (1 box)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Box 5: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  Box 5, Restricted Fragile, contains fragile originals. The material is arranged in folder order and may only be seen with permission of the appropriate curator. Preservation copies or photographic prints have been substituted in the main files for reference use.
  - Box 1, folder 2 (Box 5, Folder 118)
  - Box 1, folder 4 (Box 5, Folder 119)
  - Box 1, folder 5 (Box 5, Folder 120)
  - Box 1, folder 6 (Box 5, Folder 121)
  - Box 1, folder 7 (Box 5, Folder 122)
  - Box 1, folder 9 (Box 5, Folder 123)
  - Box 1. folder 10 (Box 5, Folder 124)
  - Box 1, folder 14 (Box 5, Folder 125)
  - Box 1, folder 15 (Box 5, Folder 126)
  - Box 1, folder 15 (Box 5, Folder 127)
  - Box 1, folder 16 (Box 5, Folder 128)
  - Box 1, folder 17 (Box 5, Folder 129)
  - Box 1, folder 18 (Box 5, Folder 130)
  - Box 1, folder 19 (Box 5, Folder 131)
  - Box 1, folder 20 (Box 5, Folder 132)
  - Box 1, folder 22 (Box 5, Folder 133)
  - Box 1, folder 32 (Box 5, Folder 134)
  - Box 2, folder 40 (Box 5, Folder 135)
  - Box 2, folder 41 (Box 5, Folder 136)
  - Box 2, folder 42 (Box 5, Folder 137)
  - Box 2, folder 44 (Box 5, Folder 138)
  - Box 2, folder 45 (Box 5, Folder 139)
  - Box 3, folder 67 (Box 5, Folder 140)
  - Box 3, folder 68 (Box 5, Folder 141)
  - Box 3, folder 71 (Box 5, Folder 142)
  - Box 3, folder 74 (Box 5, Folder 143)
  - Box 3, folder 76 (Box 5, Folder 144)
  - Box 3, folder 77 (Box 5, Folder 145)
  - Box 3, folder 80 (Box 5, Folder 146)
  - Box 3, folder 99 (Box 5, Folder 147)
  - Box 3, folder 101 (Box 5, Folder 148)